A Guide to the Papers of Henry Evans Howell, Jr. 1948-1976
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Old Dominion University
Papers of Henry Evans Howell, Jr. 1948-1976
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Old Dominion University
MG 1
199 Hollinger Document Cases; 1 Hollinger Drop-front Print Box
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Henry E. Howell, Jr. November 1974
Accruals
An additional accession of papers (1969-1977) was made in 1980. The 1980 accession is not included in this guide. Contact Special Collections for more information about these additional papers. An inventory exists, but the papers are not arranged.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry Evans Howell, Jr., was born in Norfolk, Virginia, on September 5, 1920. His father was a lumber salesman; his mother, Susan Creekmur Howell, came from Deep Creek in old Norfolk County. Mr. Howell is married to the former Elizabeth McCarty of Portsmouth and Crewe, Virginia. They have three children: Mary, Hank and Susan.
Howell attended local public schools, graduating from Maury High School in 1938. After attending the Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary (now Old Dominion University), Howell entered the Law School of the University of Virginia. He graduated with an LL.B. degree in 1943.
Howell first practiced law in West Palm Beach, Florida, but returned to Norfolk after several years. He served as law clerk to U.S. District Court Judge Sterling Hutcheson and Albert V. Bryan, and in 1948 he became associated with R. Arthur Jett with whom he formed the law firm of Jett, Sykes, and Howell in 1950. He formed a new firm - Howell, Anninos, and Daugherty (now Howell, Anninos, Daugherty, and Brown) - in 1959. Mr. Howell specializes in admiralty and tort law.
Howell first became involved in politics during Francis Pickens Miller's unsuccessful campaign for the Democratic nomination for Governor in 1949. In 1952 he served as co-manager in Norfolk for Miller's unsuccessful primary battle against Senator Harry F. Byrd. He later headed the "Volunteers for Stevenson-Kefauver" in Norfolk.
Howell first ran for political office in 1953 when he was an unsuccessful candidate in the Democratic primary for one of Norfolk's seats in the House of Delegates. His subsequent campaigns which have made him one of the best known political figures in Virginia have brought him his share of notable victories and bitter disappointments. His successes include election as a Democrat to the House of Delegates in 1959 and 1963 and to the State Senate in 1965 and 1967, and election to the Lt. Governor's office in 1971 as an independent. Howell's disappointments include a narrow loss for renomination in the 1961 Democratic primary in Norfolk, a loss to William C. Battle by less than 2% of the votes for the Democratic nomination for Governor in 1969, and a razor-thin loss in 1973 when he ran for Governor as an independent against Republican Mills Godwin.
Howell has always been a "maverick" in terms of traditional Virginia politics. He is a liberal in a basically conservative state, pro-labor in a state which strongly favors right-to-work laws, a representative of an urbanized, industrialized district in a state legislature long dominated by politicians from rural areas - the remnants of the "Byrd machine." His survival as a viable political figure under these circumstances seems attributable to his avowed stance as a "populist," a champion of the ordinary citizen against the big economic interests and their political allies. One of his key slogans has been "Keep the Big Boys Honest."
Howell has enjoyed more success against the "big boys" in the courts, both state and federal, than on the political battlefield or in the state legislature. He has brought suits against the state's poll tax, against its appropriation of federal impact funds designed to go to various localities in Virginia, and against its failure to give urban districts their due representation in the Virginia General Assembly. He has also frequently appeared as a spokesman for consumers before the State Corporation Commission to oppose rate increases requested by public utilities and insurance companies. In a number of cases he went on to file suits that eventually overthrew unfavorable S.C.C. rulings. His activity in this sphere continued during his term as Lt. Governor and after his return to private life in 1974.
In 1977 Henry Howell ran for the third time for Governor of Virginia. Although an underdog, Howell waged his usual vigorous campaign. His opponent was former Attorney General Andrew Miller in the Democratic primary. Although he out-spent and out-organized Howell, Miller met defeat. Howell received 253,373 votes (51.4%) to 239,735 (48.6%) for Miller. Howell's primary victory was attributable to support by a coalition of liberals, urban voters, blacks and organized labor. These groups tend to vote heavily in Democratic primary elections. In fact their influence in Democratic primaries is out of proportion to their number in the electorate as a whole.
Henry Howell appeared confident of his success against his Republican opponent John Dalton in the fall campaign. Once again, however, he experienced defeat. In what some analysts interpreted as a referendum on Howell himself, the voters gave Dalton a victory by 157,983 votes. Dalton received 55.9% (699,302 votes) to Howell's 43.3% (541,319 votes). Many observers believed that Howell's landslide defeat would end his political career. Nonetheless, Howell remained prominent in the liberal faction of Virginia's Democratic Party and strongly supported President Jimmy Carter for re-election in 1980.
Henry Howell died of cancer at his home in Norfolk on July 7, 1997.
Scope and Content Information
The bulk of the Howell papers deal with Mr. Howell's political career, first in Norfolk, Virginia, and, after 1968, on the statewide level as well. The specifically political papers deal with Howell's involvement in political campaigns and Democratic party affairs from 1948 through 1976. Most of this consists of correspondence, miscellaneous records, and campaign materials from his own campaigns for office, especially those for Governor in 1969 and 1973, and for Lt. Governor in 1971. Most of the newspaper clippings, pictorial and sound records, file cards, and speeches concern these campaigns. The legislative material consists of correspondence and reference material directly related to Mr. Howell's legislative activities as a Delegate (1960-1962, 1964-1966) and State Senator (1966-1971).
The legal papers consist largely of briefs and correspondence pertaining to Mr. Howell's "political" cases: suits the re-poll tax, legislative reapportionment, the use of federal impact funds, etc., as well as State Corporation Commission hearings - and related court suits re requests for rate increases by public utilities and insurance companies. They cover the period from the mid-l960's to the early 1970's. The personal papers are largely personal correspondence unrelated to Mr. Howell's legislative and legal careers. They contain some tax data but only up to 1958.
Organization
The papers are divided into twelve series:
Series I: Personal Papers (2 boxes)
Series II: Legal Papers (29 boxes)
Series III: Political Papers (1948-1973) (98 boxes)
Series IV: Legislative Papers (27 boxes)
Series V: Lt. Governorship Papers (2 boxes)
Series VI: Newspaper Clippings (27 boxes)
Series VII: Pictorial Records (1 and 1/2 boxes)
Series VIII: Sound Recordings (2 boxes)
Series IX: Memorabilia (1/2 box)
Series X: File Cards (7 boxes)
Series XI: Speeches (4 boxes)
Series XII: Political Papers 1974-1976 (1 box)
Contents List
- Personal Papers
  - Correspondence 1948 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1949 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1950 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1951 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 1952 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1953 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1956 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 1957 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence 1958 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 1960 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence 1961 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence 1963 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1964 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence 1965 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence 1966 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence 1970 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence January-April 1971 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence May-December 1971 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence 1972 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence 1973 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 24)
  - American Institute of Banking (Commercial Law Course): Correspondence 1951-1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Institute of Banking(Texts and class records for commercial law course) 1951-1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church affairs at St. Andrew's Episcopal Church 1949-1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Income Tax material 1949-1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Insurance material 1939-1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous material 1945-1955 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Real Estate material 1951-1957 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
- Legal Papers 1948-1966
  - General
    - Legal Papers 1948 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Legal Papers 1949 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Legal Papers 1950 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Legal Papers 1951 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Legal Papers 1952 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Legal Papers 1953 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Legal Papers 1954 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Legal Papers 1955 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Legal Papers 1956 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Legal Papers 1957 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Legal Papers January-September 1958 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Legal Papers October-December, 1958 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Legal Papers January-August, 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Legal Papers September-December, 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Legal Papers 1960 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Legal Papers 1961 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Legal Papers 1962 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Legal Papers 1963 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Legal Papers 1964 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Legal Papers 1964 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Legal Papers 1965 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Legal Papers 1966 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Legal Papers 1967 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Legal Papers 1968 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Legal Papers 1970 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Legal Papers 1971 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Legal Papers 1972 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Legal Papers 1973 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Legal Papers 1973 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Legal Papers (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Legal Papers C & O R.R.Cases 1953, 1956 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Legal Papers:William Dalgarno Case 1953-1954 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Legal Papers:Miscellaneous materials re: Seamen's Unions 1951-1954 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mann V. Davis (Virginia Reaportionment)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Original Complaint 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Miscellaneous Pleadings by Original Plaintiffs 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Trial Brief; Reply of Original Plaintiffs(Mann) 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Howell Intervention; Complaint and Miscellaneous Pleadings 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Brief and Reply Brief of Howell Interveners 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Deposition of Ralph Einsenberg 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Pleadings by Defendants (Davis, Fairfax Co., Arlington Co.) 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Transcripts of Testimony 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Court Orders 1962 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Majority and Dissenting Opinions 1962 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Notice of Appeal by Defendants; Record of Appeal 1962 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Plaintiff's Effort to get "Order on Mandate" of Supreme Court 1964 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; order on Mandate; Opinion on Order on Mandate 1964 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Pleadings re: State's Application for Stay of Order on Mandate 1964 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Intervention by Henrico Co. Group 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Exhibits of Henrico Co. Interveners 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Exhibits of Henrico Co. Interveners 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Exhibits of Henrico Co. Interveners 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Intervention by Richmond Group 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Intervention by Shenandoah Group 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; State Response to Richmond and Henrico Interveners 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Decisions re: Shenandoah, Richmond, Henrico Interventions 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Acceptance of Final Court Orders 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Correspondence Prior to Verdict 1962 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Correspondence Post Verdict 1962 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Newspaper Clippings 1962 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Correspondence 1965 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Reference material from U.va. Bureau of Public Administration 1962 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; National Municipal League; Correspondence and Reference Material 1962 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Reference material from Ralph Eisenberg(U.Va.) 1962 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Data re: Previous Redistrictions 1962 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. District Court; Miscellaneous Data on Reapportionment 1961-1963 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Motion for Stay of District Court Order 1962-1963 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Pleadings by Appellants (State of Virginia) 1963 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Briefs for Appellees(Howell) 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Briefs for U.S. as "Amicus Curiae," 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Decision; Decisions in Related Cases 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Index to Appeal Record 1962-1964 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Va. Effort to Obtain Stay of Lower Court Order 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Appeal by Henrico Interveners 1965 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Briefs in related Maryland Case 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Briefs by U.S. in Related Cases 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Briefs in Related N.Y. Case 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Correspondence 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Mann v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; U.S. Supreme Court; Correspondence 1964 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Tyler & Jett V. Davis (Va. Reapportionment)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Norfolk; Bill of Complaint for Injunction 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Norfolk; Bill of Complaint (Copy II) 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Norfolk; Application for Injunction 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Norfolk; Motion to Dismiss; Draft Order for Transfer to Richmond 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Miscellaneous Pleadings by Plaintiffs 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Miscellaneous Pleadings by Defendants 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Transcript June 5, 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Transcripts June 6,1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Decision; Final Order 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Notice of Appeal 1964 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Supreme Court; Final Disposition of Case 1965 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Miscellaneous Reference Material 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Norfolk; Correspondence 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Correspondence 1963 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Tyler & Jett v. Davis: Va. Reapportionment; Va. Circuit Court, Richmond; Va. Supreme Court; Correspondence re: Howell Appeal 1963-1964 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Wilkins v. Davis (Congressional Redistricting)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; Pleading by Petitioners (Wilkins) 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; Pleading by Defendants (Davis) 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; Depositions for Petitioners-J.L. Lancaster, Mrs. Leslie Curdts, Dr. Loring Thompson 1964 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; Depostions for Petitioners-J.R. Coyle, T.R. Reed, S.Forbes 1964 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; Depostions for Defendants - G. A. Treakle, J. M. Tusing, W. F. Duckworth 1964 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; Defense Depositions - Watkins Abbitt, H. W. Smith, Joel Broyhill, J. M. Magruder 1964 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; Court Orders; Final Decision 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Va. Supreme Court; General Correspondence 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; U.S. District Court; Miscellaneous Pleadings 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; U.S. District Court; Court Order Postponing Hearing Case; Draft Order for Dismissal 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; U.S. District Court; General Corresondence 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Reference Material; Data re: Norfolk 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Reference Material; 1960 census for Norfolk and Portsmouth 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Reference Material; Planning Data for the Southeast Va. region 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Reference Material; Data on Virginia 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Reference Material; Maps 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Wilkins v. Davis: Congressional Redistricting; Reference Material; Pleadings in Brown v. Saunders Redistricting Suit 1934 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Davis v. Dusch: Virginia Beach Redistricting
    - davis v. Dusch: Va Beach Redistricting; General; Miscellaneous Data re: Va. Beach 1964-1967 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Davis v. Dusch: Va Beach Redistricting; General; Miscellaneous Data re: Municipal Government in Va. 1964-1967 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Davis v. Dusch: Va Beach Redistricting; General; Miscellaneous Material re; Reapportionment 1964-1967 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Davis v. Dusch: Va Beach Redistricting; General; Va. Beach Council Proposals re: Redistricting 1965 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Davis v. Dusch: Va Beach Redistricting; General; Correspondence re: Local Government and Redistricting 1965-1969 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Davis v. Dusch: Va Beach Redistricting; General; Va. Supreme Court; Pleadings by Petitioners (Howell) 1964 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Davis v. Dusch: Va Beach Redistricting; General; Va. Supreme Court; Pleadings by Defendants 1964 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 11)